<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Games on Vasuman</title>
    <link>https://varav.in/games/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Games on Vasuman</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>varav@varav.in (Vasuman Ravichandran)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>varav@varav.in (Vasuman Ravichandran)</webMaster>
    
	<atom:link href="https://varav.in/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Ator</title>
      <link>https://varav.in/games/ator/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>varav@varav.in (Vasuman Ravichandran)</author>
      <guid>https://varav.in/games/ator/</guid>
      <description>Ator  Ator is a game in which the player controls the motion of the character by tilting the device. As the device tilts, the perspective of the camera also tilts giving the illusion of a fixed surface. The player taps on the screen to fire in that direction.
The ground texture is supposed to give you a techno-feel. Most 3D models in this game are platonic solids or shapes that can be rigged in less than 3 steps in Blender.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Box, Hop! Box</title>
      <link>https://varav.in/games/bhb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>varav@varav.in (Vasuman Ravichandran)</author>
      <guid>https://varav.in/games/bhb/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Box, Hop! Box&amp;rdquo; is a game where the objective is to keep climbing while avoiding the edges of the screen and falling boxes.
I originally made this for js13k for which the theme was reversal. Hence, the flipping controller. I messed up the final submission and the result is that it only works in browsers that support a few ES6 features. The version on this site works fine though.
It was mainly designed to be played on touchscreen devices.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Glitchball</title>
      <link>https://varav.in/games/glitchball/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>varav@varav.in (Vasuman Ravichandran)</author>
      <guid>https://varav.in/games/glitchball/</guid>
      <description>div.play-button-container { text-align: center; font-size: x-large; margin: 1.5em; } span.play-button  a { padding: 0.3em 1.5em; border: 5px outset #666; background-color: #333; text-decoration: none; color: white; }  Play   Rules   There are two players and the aim of this game is to get the ball (yellow thing) to the other players goal.
  Once you have the ball, if the other player touches you, you die and respawn next to your goal and the other player gets possesion of the ball.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>