<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Vasuman</title><link>https://www.varav.in/</link><description>Recent content on Vasuman</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://www.varav.in/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Apoha: Meaning Via Exclusion</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/apoha/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/apoha/</guid><description>&lt;p>At its core, the raw content of our experience consists of a distinct set of
sense perceptions that we&amp;rsquo;ve perhaps never encountered before. And yet, we
somehow manage to make sense of them, by mapping these unique concrete
particulars to more familiar abstract universals.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Indrajala: The Infinite Web</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/indrajala/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/indrajala/</guid><description>In 17th century London, John Donne fell deathly ill. The field of pathophysiology wasn&amp;rsquo;t much of a thing back then and sickness was considered a manifestation of sin that warranted a visit from God. Rather than rest through the anguish, Donne decided to chronicle his reflections during this period. Fortunately, he survived and eventually published these reflections in a volume, Devotions Upon Emergent Occasions. The most famous of these meditations is perhaps familiar to many.</description></item><item><title>The Anarchy in Science</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/anarchy-science/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/anarchy-science/</guid><description>Reading an introductory science textbook gives you the impression that there is a clear, well-defined structure to the scientific process. You start with an observation, develop a hypothesis that is consistent with existing theories, run an experiment to test it, and collect the results. If the findings match your model, you&amp;rsquo;ve got a working theory. Otherwise, you refine your hypothesis, rinse your instruments and repeat until it does.
While a neat definition that fits on a flash card makes for a good exam question, does it accurately reflect reality?</description></item><item><title>The Art of Suspending Judgement</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/suspending-judgement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/suspending-judgement/</guid><description>The modern human is conditioned to think in terms of strict dichotomies.
News reports must be judged as real or fake. One’s political beliefs must belong exclusively to the left or the right. The existence of a higher power must either be constantly affirmed or vehemently denied.
We’re forced to choose between two extremes. And led to believe that a refusal to endorse one position is tacit support for its opposite.</description></item><item><title>Beyond Logical Consistency</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/paraconsistent-logic/</link><pubDate>Fri, 21 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/paraconsistent-logic/</guid><description>&lt;p>We conventionally associate the term logic with bivalent logic. A system in
which any proposition is assigned just one of two possible values: true or
false. But, what if there was more to it?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Work Less To Do More</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/resting/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/resting/</guid><description>The prominence of #hustlelife posts on Instagram reflects the values of our current times. The capitalistic society we live in glorifies overwork and vilifies rest. We are led to believe that any time not spent on so-called &amp;ldquo;productive&amp;rdquo; labor is a sinful waste that must be diverted to more useful endeavors.
Stories of successful people who are constantly working litter our cultural mythos &amp;mdash; like CEOs who sleep on the factory floor while personally overseeing production.</description></item><item><title>Transcendence Through Negation</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/apotheism/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/apotheism/</guid><description>Philo Judaeus was a Jewish philosopher from Alexandria, who lived contemporaneous with the Christ. While Jesus walked around extolling the positive attributes of a unitary God: compassionate, merciful, loving, kind. Philo preferred a different approach to describing the absolute &amp;mdash; by negating characterizations.
In Philo&amp;rsquo;s allegorical exegesis on the Old Testament in Greek, he spurned the anthropomorphization of God. His view on human-like descriptions of God in scripture was that they were not to be taken literally, but instead considered metaphors.</description></item><item><title>Observing Things As They Are</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/yathabhutam/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/yathabhutam/</guid><description>I recently completed a 10-day Vipassana retreat, which was a pretty enlightening experience. I’d highly recommend it to anyone seeking to reduce their suffering. I learned a lot, but my key takeaway from the entire exercise is that our suffering arises from not accepting the reality of things as they are.
Our minds are constantly engaged in constructing a fictional ideal world conditioned by our desires while heedlessly ignoring the true nature of things.</description></item><item><title>Shunyata: The Emptiness of Essence</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/shunyata/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/shunyata/</guid><description>For millennia, philosophers have debated whether essences (svabhāva) are real entities. In the West, the essentialist doctrine was famously espoused by Plato’s Theory of Ideas which claimed that real-world objects are imitations of transcendent Forms.
In his book The History of Western Philosophy, Bertrand Russell criticizes this view, claiming that it conflates a linguistic convention with metaphysical ontology.
We apply the same name, on different occasions, to somewhat different occurrences, which we regard as manifestations of a single “thing” or “person”.</description></item><item><title>Perspectives on Issue Tracking</title><link>https://www.varav.in/articles/issue-tracking/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://www.varav.in/articles/issue-tracking/</guid><description>Bugs, issues, tickets: They go by many names but serve the same purpose&amp;mdash;tracking a task that needs to get done. It&amp;rsquo;s the lifeblood of project management in the tech industry, where nothing gets done that isn&amp;rsquo;t tracked somehow. And, like most invented concepts, it&amp;rsquo;s simply a formalization of our innate ways of thinking about tasks.
Humans have probably been trying to quantify work ever since we started hunting together. But modern-day project management traces its lineage back to 1911 when Frederick Taylor published The Principles of Scientific Management, which aimed at systemizing the job of an individual worker to maximize output for the enterprise.</description></item></channel></rss>